Philip Singer Papers
Philip Singer Papers
1883-2016
Singer, Philip, 1925-
38.25 linear ft.
Correspondence, writings, and research material of medical anthropologist and filmmaker Philip Singer. Collection includes a substantial amount of audio- and videorecordings.
5068972
Biographical History
Philip Singer (1925-2016) was a medical anthropologist and documentary filmmaker.
Singer was born in Ohio on April 16, 1925. Not much is known about his early and personal life, but he received his doctorate from Syracuse University in 1961. His dissertation, Hindu Holy Men: A Study in Charisma, was based on fieldwork among Indian ascetics (sadhus). At Syracuse, Singer was closely associated with Ernest Becker (1924-1974), the Pulitzer-Prize winning author of The Denial of Death (1973), and with Swami Agehananda Bharati (1923-1991), a Sanskrit scholar and Hindu monk who taught at Syracuse for more than three decades.
Singer went on to conduct long-term research among Hindus in British Guiana (now Guyana), on the northern coast of South America. While serving on the faculty at Albany Medical College (1961-67), he studied Kali Mai, a Hindu mother-goddess cult in rural Guyana. In 1963, he began to work intimately with Jamsie Naidoo (1913-1997), the leading figure in the revival of the Kali Mai tradition, which has now taken root in Indo-Guyanese communities in several North American cities, including New York, Orlando, Tampa, and Toronto. From 1967 until his retirement in 2002, Singer was Professor of Anthropology and Behavioral Sciences at Oakland University in Rochester, Michigan.
In 1974, Singer used 16mm film to document field work that he had been conducting in Guyana. He later used that footage to make his first film, Divine Madness: Trance, Dance and Healing in Guyana (1978). Over his career, he directed and produced more than 60 ethnographic films and other documentaries, including Medicine Woman, Medicine Man: Traditional Holistic Medicine in Middle America (1985), The Haitians, the Healers, and the Anthropologist (1997), The Last Interview of Thomas Szasz, M.D. (2013), and Final Participant Observation: Senior Cultural Anthropologists Confront Their Mortality (2016). Singer was also the founding partner of Traditional Healing Productions, a film production company. Philip Singer died in New York City in 2016 at the age of 91.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Philip Singer Papers contains correspondence, journal articles, interviews, notes, research files, and audiovisual materials relating to Singer's research and films. The collection includes more than 400 audio recordings, 600 videotapes and recordings, and 550 DVDs. The collection has been divided into seven series.
Correspondence contains Singer's correspondence with a handful of recipients. The correspondence mostly pertains to Singer's work as an anthropologist and his films.
The Films contains material relating to Singer's films. Films with a significant amount of material are: Circo Rois (2005), Complementary Health Therapies in England (1993), Conventional and Unconventional Practitioners of Alternative Medicine in the USA (1996), Final Participant Observation: Senior Cultural Anthropologists Confront Their Mortality (2016), The Last Interview of Thomas Szasz (2013), The Last Mattanza (1999), One of the Mad Ones (2011), Sicilian Women Orgasm -- Vaginal or Clitoral? (2001), and Traditional Healing Nigeria (1979). For each film, manuscript material is listed first and any recordings related to that film last. Manuscript material may include correspondence, interview transcripts, notes, research, reviews, and scripts. Recordings may include raw footage, trailers, promos, audio recordings, VHS commercial tapes, and DVD transfers.
Note that when [Copy 1] or [Copy 2] appears after a title it is an indication that the items are identical copies. Other items may appear to be identical based on title and format, but either there are small physical differences (in the DVD artwork, for example) or we are unable to verify that they are truly identical.
Memorabilia contains clippings about Singer, and a few photographs of conference events and oversized commercial photographs.
Research files contains Singer's research material on topics related to non-traditional medicine practiced in cultures all over the world. Topics include alternative medicine, bee sting therapy, depression, dowsing, folk medicine, hypnosis, phenylketonuria (PKU), schizophrenia, shamanism, and suicide. Medical practices in Africa, Cuba, Guyana, Italy, and Russia are also explored within his research files. Singer also researched and worked with non-traditional medical practitioners such as Native American healer Wanita Windwalker, unorthodox psychologist Daniel DeSole, Guyana healer Jamsie Naidoo, and Nigerian Chief Lambo. Additionally, in this series you can find Singer's research material relating to depression, right-to-die, and suicide. Because of Singer's interest in the topics of depression and suicide, there are files regarding Mexican artist Frida Kahlo and her supposed suicide after suffering from serious health conditions that resulted in the loss of her leg. Singer also studied difficult and graphic subject matter: there are files relating to clitoridectomy (female circumcision) and subincision (the manipulation of male genitalia found in Australian native cultures). These folders contain graphic content which researchers may find disturbing.
The series is arranged alphabetically by research topic. Within each topic, manuscript material is listed first followed by any recordings – not all topics have corresponding recordings. Recordings may include television recordings, audio recordings, filmed lectures or conferences, and commercial films.
Teaching files consists of Singer's lecture notes and research.
Writings is comprised of drafts, notes, and published items. Most of the writings are journal articles; there are a few book and film reviews that Singer wrote for academic journals.
Finally, Miscellaneous media contains audiovisual materials that did not fit within the Films or Research files series. These materials cover a wide variety of subjects and genres. There are personal recordings of conferences and lectures; home recordings; television recordings; commercial recordings; and raw footage that is not clearly linked to a particular film. Formats range from audio cassettes, CDs, DVDs, VHS, Hi8 tapes, MiniDVs, and USBs. There is also a single U-matic tape.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically, except for the Miscellaneous media, which is listed at the end. Within the Films and Research files series manuscript material is listed first followed by any recordings. Recordings are arranged physically by ID#, but are listed in the inventory in their logical location, and as a result, related recordings may be in several different boxes.
Subject and Genre Headings
Religion and philosophy; Science and medicine; DeSole, Daniel E.; Kahlo, Frida.; Singer, Philip, 1925-; Szasz, Thomas Stephen, 1920-2012.; Windwalker, Wanita, 1929-1979.; Alternative medicine.; Anthropology of religion.; Bee stings.; Coma.; Dowsing.; Hypnotism.; Medical anthropology.; Mental health.; Phenylketonuria.; Schizophrenia.; Sex -- Anthropological aspects.; Shamanism.; Suicide.; Traditional medicine.; Women -- Health and hygiene.; Africa.; Italy.; Mexico.; South America.; Articles.; Audiocassettes.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Documentary films.; DVDs.; Hi-8.; Lectures.; Photographs.; Research notes.; Sound recordings.; Video recordings (physical artifacts); VHS.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Access to audiovisual material requires advance notice to produce a use copy.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Paula Singer, 2018.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Brooks, Richard, 1980-1990 (Box 1)
  - Catholic Social Services/St. Vincent Home for Children, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Eisenberg, David M.D., 1993 (Box 1)
  - Ernest Becker Foundation, 1998; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Glass, Philip, 2007 (Box 1)
  - La Ban, Myron M.D., 1988 (Box 1)
  - Okolie, Tony, 2003 (Box 1)
  - "P + E", 1976; postcard (Box 1)
  - Savimbi, Samuel Atta, 2003 (Box 1)
- Films
  When [Copy 1] or [Copy 2] appears after a title it is an indication that the items are identical copies. Other items may appear to be identical based on title and format, but either there are small physical differences (in the DVD artwork, for example) or we are unable to verify that they are truly identical.
  - Film bibliography/reference, undated; listed first in series as a reference for Singer's films (Box 59)
  - AIDS: A Cautionary Tale
    - Review, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Recordings
      - AIDS: A Cautionary Tale, singer_p_1264; text on disc: "mind, body, spirit, herbs, drugs"; DVD; running time 52:00 (Oversize 6)
      - AIDS: A Cautionary Tale, singer_p_1265; text on disc: "mind, body, spirit, herbs, drugs"; DVD; running time 52:00 (Oversize 6)
      - AIDS: A Cautionary Tale, singer_p_1282; text on case: "mind, body, spirit, herbs, drugs"; DVD; running time 52:00 (Oversize 6)
      - AIDS: A Cautionary Tale, singer_p_1409; handwritten text on case: "mind-body-spirit-herbs-drugs-AIDS"; DVD; running time 49:00 (Box 55)
  - Allan Kardee Spiritist Movement documentary, 2007; NF logs (Box 1)
  - Anthropologist and Informant: Whose Film? Whose Truth?
    - Recordings
      - Anthropologist and Informant: Whose Film? Whose Truth?, singer_p_0988; label on disc, "J. Naidu comhents [sic], hail mother Kali, trance, dance, healing"; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 4)
      - Anthropologist and Informant: Whose Film? Whose Truth?, singer_p_0989; label on disc, "J. Naidu comhents (sic), hail mother Kali, trance, dance, healing"; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 4)
      - Anthropologist and Informant: Whose Film? Whose Truth?, singer_p_0990; label on disc, "J. Naidu comhents (sic), hail mother Kali, trance, dance, healing"; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 4)
  - The Anthropologist and the Santera: Participant Observation or Clinical Anthropology
    - Recordings
      - The Anthropologist and the Santera: Participant Observation or Clinical Anthropology?, singer_p_1090; DVD; running time 57:00 (Oversize 5)
      - The Anthropologist and the Santera: Participant Observation or Clinical Anthropology?, singer_p_1091; DVD; running time 57:00 (Oversize 5)
      - The Anthropologist and the Santera: Participant Observation or Clinical Anthropology?, singer_p_1092; DVD; running time 57:00 (Oversize 5)
  - The Anthropologist and the Santera Priestess: Participant Observation or Clinical Anthropology?
    - Recordings
      - The Anthropologist and the Santera Priestess: Participant Observation or Clinical Anthropology?, singer_p_1094; DVD; running time 58:00 (Oversize 5)
      - The Anthropologist and the Santera Priestess: Participant Observation or Clinical Anthropology?, singer_p_1305; DVD; running time 57:00 (Oversize 6)
  - Bee Venom Therapy for Multiple Sclerosis
    - Recordings
      - Bee Venom Therapy for Multiple Sclerosis, singer_p_0001; a discussion video, includes Philip Singer business card; VHS; running time 42:00 (Box 25)
      - Bee Venom Therapy for Multiple Sclerosis (Master), singer_p_0002; VHS; running time 42:00 (Box 25)
  - Circo Rois
    - Critical review, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Emails, 2003-2004; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - La Mattanza, treatment by Emelise Aleandri, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Minetti, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 2004 (Box 23)
    - Research notes, undated (Box 59)
    - Review, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Review, Oakland University Journal, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Stabil #1, undated (Box 1)
    - Conference submissions, 1996-2014 (Box 1)
    - Recordings
      - Circo '05 Setting Up Show, singer_p_1436; DVD; running time 110:00 (Box 55)
      - Circo Rois, 2005; singer_p_1296; handwritten label on disc reads, "girls - interviews, show"; DVD; running time 35:00 (Box 52)
      - [Circo Rois] #1, 2003; singer_p_0247; label provides this description of raw footage: "1st day circus"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #2, 2003; singer_p_0248; label provides this description: "1st nite circus, breaking down circus"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #2 DVD transfer, 2005; singer_p_0269; label provides this description: "Remorchiu more forgiving to Noemi - who had depression, bulimia"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #3, 2003; singer_p_0249; label provides this description: "Continues circus, prepares food in trailer"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #3 DVD transfer, 2005; singer_p_0270; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #4, 2003; singer_p_0250; label provides this description: "Posters - Bain Latina, strong [illegible] with limited space"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #4 DVD transfer, 2005; singer_p_0271; interviews, girls performance; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #5, 2003; singer_p_0251; label provides this description: "From 8:15-11:15 - Setting up circus"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #6, 2003; singer_p_0252; label provides this description: "Bail Latina - performance, poor turnout for performance, show must go on; I 'buy' 2nd show for E100 Agnes [illegible] they will [prove?] one show before I leave only for me; photos of family; discuss future"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #7, 2003; singer_p_0253; label provides this description: "Bail Latina; Performance 2x; [illegible] angry because [illegible] for 2nd show - she wants to go to disco; shots of commence; [two more descriptions that are illegible]"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #8, 2003; singer_p_0272; label on tape provides this description: "4/27 Sunday Baia Latina, taking tent down, Monday am"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #9, 2003; singer_p_0273; label on tape provides this description: "Move to Prata, May 1-5; 6 trips lock-forth, Prata 20 km away, old towns here, no movie only lines - circus only; putting up posters"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #10, 2003; singer_p_0254; label provides this description: "Prata; Putting up tent; fight with - She wants to [illegible] a tent for a wedding, he says first work, then dress; 4/30 entire family in trailer [illegible]"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #11, 2003; singer_p_0255; label provides this description of raw footage for the film Circo Rois: "Fool born; Interview and memo circus"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #12, 2003; singer_p_0256; label provides this description: "Snake wash; May 2 - good turnout, good performance, circus lottery; May 3 laying snake lox, clean UR"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #13, 2003; singer_p_0274; label on tape provides this description: "Cleaning up; breeding ponies; good crowd at Prata circus Sat first good crowd in 10 days; girls practice dance"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #14, 2003; singer_p_0257; label provides this description: "Sunday brunch; PS baptism; Interview with friends of circus"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #15, 2003; singer_p_0275; label on tape provides this description: "Dismantling tent"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #16, 2003; singer_p_0258; label provides this description: "Go to residence [illegible] to see about identity card for Hena who lost hers; go to [illegible] to see about paying to be - after collapsing mail services tent; publicity from about [illegible]; Interview with Ilenia"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #17, 2003; singer_p_0259; label provides this description: "Move from Prato to Capriati; Interview with Ilenia, Noeve, Jones"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #18, 2003; singer_p_0260; label provides this description: "May 9 - day starts - Capriati; setting up tent"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #19, 2003; singer_p_0261; label provides this description: "5/9 - No show for circus Friday PM; Vaironce - shopping for Sunday, shots of mama shopping; 5/10 performance - interviews with circus attendees by 'Antonio'; 5/11 Washing snake"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #20, 2003; singer_p_0276; label on tape provides this description: "washing snake; snake eats children"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #21, 2003; singer_p_0262; label provides this description: "5/12 No show - tent down circus; 5/13 girls angry and they don't like pizza - nowhere to go - boy - disco, etc., shots of breakfast; Flenia shoots"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #22, 2003; singer_p_0263; label provides this description: "5/14-15 Ilenia shoots; Enel cuts off poles; [illegible]; Buying cheap diesel gas 8o cents less per liter, Monte [illegible] cemetery"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #23, 2003; singer_p_0264; label provides this description: "Ilenia shoots; [rebair?] brooks; Ilenia caravan; Ilenia shoots cuisine; Il-Naeni watch soap; Ilenia PS"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #24, 2003; singer_p_0265; label provides this description: "Noemi, Ilenia shoots"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #25, 2003; singer_p_0392; label provides this description: "Family interview with talk of circus future; interview with Pino [end of video]"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 46)
      - [Circo Rois] #26, 2003; singer_p_0266; label provides this description: "5/20 Capriati"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - [Circo Rois] #27, 2003; singer_p_0267; label provides this description: "Negros; Big circus; Poster/calendars/tickets y mapa"; MiniDV; running time 60:00 (Box 44)
      - Circo Rois: Che Bella Vita, singer_p_1144; English subtitles; DVD; running time 60:00 (Box 52)
      - Circo Rois: Che Bella Vita, singer_p_1141; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 5)
      - Circo Rois: Che Bella Vita, singer_p_1151; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 5)
      - Circo Rois: Che Bella Vita (King Circus: What a Beautiful Life), singer_p_1143; English subtitles; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 5)
      - Circo Rois: Che Bella Vita (King Circus: What a Beautiful Life), singer_p_1150; English subtitles; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 5)
      - Circo Rois: Che Bella Vita (What a Beautiful Life), singer_p_1142; English subtitles; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 5)
      - Circo Rois: Che Bella Vita (What a Beautiful Life), Campania, Italy, singer_p_1072; English subtitles; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 5)
      - Circo Rois: Che Bella Vita (What a Beautiful Life), Campania, Italy, singer_p_1073; English subtitles; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 5)
      - Circo Rois: Che Bella Vita, Campania, Italy, singer_p_1145; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 5)
      - Circo Rois: Che Bella Vita, Campania, Italy, singer_p_1146; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 5)
      - Circo Rois: Che Bella Vita, Campania, Italy, singer_p_1147; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 5)
      - Circo Rois, Che Bella Vita (What A Beautiful Life), Campania, Italy, singer_p_1388; English subtitles; DVD; running time 60:00 (Box 55)
      - Circo Rois (King Circus) "What A Wonderful Life", singer_p_1300; English subtitles; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 6)
      - Circo Rois (King Circus) "What A Wonderful Life", singer_p_1301; English subtitles; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 6)
      - Circo Rois (King Circus) "What A Wonderful Life", singer_p_1302; English subtitles; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 6)
      - Circo Rois: Mimo, singer_p_1149; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 5)
      - Circo Rois: Remorchio, singer_p_1148; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 5)
  - Complementary Health Therapies in England, multiple titles in a series of films
    - Review, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Recordings
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England Previews, singer_p_1400; DVD; running time 30:00 (Box 55)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: Acupuncture for Pain Relief [Copy 1], singer_p_0005; includes Philip Singer business card; VHS; running time 56:12 (Box 25)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: Acupuncture for Pain Relief [Copy 2], singer_p_0006; includes Philip Singer business card; VHS; running time 56:12 (Box 25)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: Aromatherapy in a Cardiac Post-Surgery Ward, 1992; singer_p_1085; DVD; running time 31:00 (Oversize 5)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: Aromatherapy in a Cardiac Post-Surgery Ward, singer_p_1427; DVD; running time 31:00 (Box 55)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: Aromatherapy in a Cardiac Post-Surgery Ward [Copy 1], singer_p_0007; includes Philip Singer business card; VHS; running time 31:00 (Box 25)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: Aromatherapy in a Cardiac Post-Surgery Ward [Copy 2], singer_p_0010; includes Philip Singer business card; VHS; running time 31:00 (Box 25)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: Homeopathy, singer_p_1185; label on case reads, "Royal London homeopathy health, interviews with patients, pharmacist, ward bed patients, Hale Clinic, London"; DVD; running time 60:00 (Oversize 5)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: Homeopathy "Let Like Cure Like" [Copy 1], singer_p_0008; includes business card for Philip Singer; VHS; running time 45:00 (Box 25)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: Homeopathy "Let Like Cure Like" [Copy 2], singer_p_0009; includes business card for Philip Singer; VHS; running time 45:00 (Box 25)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: "Let Like Cure Like" Homeopathy, singer_p_0997; interviews with physicians, patients, pharmacists; DVD; running time 45:00 (Oversize 4)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: "Let Like Cure Like" Homeopathy, singer_p_0998; interviews with physicians, patients, pharmacists; DVD; running time 45:00 (Oversize 4)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: "Let Like Cure Like" Homeopathy, singer_p_0999; interviews with physicians, patients, pharmacists; DVD; running time 45:00 (Oversize 4)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: #8 The Church and Health Care Delivery, singer_p_0014; includes Philip Singer business card; VHS; running time 56:26 (Box 26)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England #9: Talk and Touch Therapeutic Massage, singer_p_1309; DVD; running time 50:00 (Oversize 6)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: #10 Osteopathy in England (Master), singer_p_0011; VHS; running time 27:30 (Box 25)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: #10 Osteopathy in England [Copy 1], singer_p_0012; includes Philip Singer business card; VHS; running time 27:30 (Box 25)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: #10 Osteopathy in England [Copy 2], singer_p_0013; includes Philip Singer business card; VHS; running time 27:30 (Box 25)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England #10: Osteopathy, singer_p_1290; DVD; running time 27:00 (Oversize 6)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: Sampler, singer_p_1428; DVD; running time 13:00 (Box 55)
      - Complementary Health Therapies in England: Spiritual Healing Part II An Interview with the Spiritual Healer (Master), singer_p_0021; VHS; running time 23:37 (Box 26)